National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records, 1974-1999
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
- SERIES II. PROGRAMS 1975-1996, 28 linear ft.
  The Support services subseries includes administrative records on the childcare, counseling and referral services which NCNW offered to participants in most of their local programs. Although sensitive material has been removed, there are interesting discussions on counseling sessions in the counselor's meeting minutes and social work interns' reports where the subjects are not named. Related counseling material can be found in under Education-College program, and in the job counseling files under Employment-Job development. There is also related material on support groups and the Leadership Support Process (LSP) filed under Leadership. Related material on childcare services can be found under Employment-World of Work-Childcare training and Youth programs which offered childcare instruction and services for teenage mothers.
  The Community and economic development subseries documents NCNW projects which aimed to create a network with other grassroots leaders to research and dialogue on issues of female poverty and community development, and to formulate a cohesive strategy to influence public policy at state and national levels. The projects documented here are central to the principles and vision of NCNW and overarch of most other programs. Material related to a survey conducted for the Women in Neighborhoods Project (1979-80), NCNW's first project with a national scope, is included in this section. Its survey of thirty neighborhood organizations was an effort to analyze the role of women in community activism. Results showed that although neighborhood women initiated many community development projects, once funding was received, women were usually excluded from the planning and execution of the programs. The survey solicited important information from a geographically, racially, and ethnically diverse population of low-income women. The records include the published report of the project, Neighborhood Women: Putting it Together.
  Other projects documented here include the Women in Poverty Project (1980-82) which identified community resources benefiting impoverished women through a series of questionnaires, and conducted leadership training sessions held throughout the region [see also Leadership]; the National Resource and Policy Analysis Center in Washington, D.C. (1981-82) which aimed to collect information on federal programs and policies affecting poor and working-class women and to disseminate that information to women leaders and organizations. The Dialogues on Community Development and Female Poverty (1983-) as well as NCNW's annual Community Development Institute (1990-) have served to bring together a diverse group of grassroots activists and scholars for networking and strategizing. The 1986 conference on "Women in Community Development: Forging a National Alliance with International Linkages," co-sponsored by the Overseas Education Fund, reflects NCNW's beginnings in the growing international Women and Development Movement [see also International]. The Subject files at end of this subseries include articles and papers that outline NCNW's community and economic development agenda.
  The Education subseries documents its flagship projects, the community-based College Program, as well as its adult education program. The College Program (1975- ), originally funded by the Rockefeller Brothers Foundation, was started to provide "interdisciplinary course work augmented with apprenticeship in the community" for women in Williamsburg-Greenpoint. In collaboration with area community colleges, courses leading toward an Associates degree focused on neighborhood studies and community development and gave students the necessary knowledge and skills to become more effective leaders in their communities. In 1982, a Bachelor's degree program was added. As the first program of its kind, the College program has served as model for similar programs elsewhere in the country. Materials included here document the administrative and planning of the program, and curriculum development. Also included are papers written by students, publicity, and conference material.
  Recognizing that many single mothers and other low-income women lacked sufficient education to enter their College program and job training programs, NCNW, in conjunction with New York City's Board of Education, introduced pre-College adult education courses in the 1980s. These include classes in literacy, math, English as a second language, and preparation for the high school equivalency degree (G.E.D.). Classes were also offered for women at public housing sites, in conjunction with employment and leadership training [see also Housing and tenants], and in 1986, NCNW opened the "You Can" Community School, an alternative program for young high school dropouts. [See also Youth.]
  The Employment subseries documents NCNW's local projects that provide job skills training, job development, counseling and job placement for low-income women. After the General administrative files, the projects are arranged chronologically from the date of inception. The first, Project Open Doors (P.O.D.) was started by the Women's Funding Coalition of over thirty community and women's organizations in New York City, and funded by New York's Department of Employment under the Comprehensive Employment Training Act (CETA). [See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Development.] NCNW was the administrator of the project and provided support services through its Job Development program. Hundreds of low-income women were placed in apprenticeship positions with the participating organizations which included women's shelters, health clinics, rape crisis centers, and other community agencies. [For additional files on these organizations, including the Women's Funding Coalition, see SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS]. The Job Development Program, concurrent with P.O.D., offered career counseling, skills assessment and referrals to jobs and remedial education courses. [See also Education program.] In addition, NCNW offered workshops in resume preparation, job searching, networking, and work place issues such as stress management, sexual harassment, childcare, and unions. Included here are questionnaires and a report from a neighborhood "job analysis" done by NCNW. Based on this employment needs assessment NCNW developed a more intensive Employment and Training program in 1982, offering job skills training in computer repair, programming, and word processing. Beginning in 1985, NCNW also offered an employment orientation course, "World of Work," with workshops on interviewing techniques, resume writing, and job search skills. Additional material on World of Work and job training can be found under Women's Public Works, Housing and tenants, and Youth.
  The Housing and tenant subseries is arranged in two sections: the first focuses on grassroots efforts to create affordable housing for women on local, national and international levels; and second documents NCNW's training and support programs for public housing tenants in the New York City area. The Housing section includes a project of the Greenpoint Renaissance Enterprise Corporation (GREC), co-founded by NCNW, to convert an abandoned hospital complex into affordable inter-generational housing designed by a feminist architectural firm in the 1980s. [See also SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS-St. Nicholas Neighborhood Preservation Corporation; and the Williamsburg-Greenpoint Community Planning Board.] This section also includes material on the international conference, "Housing Options for Women" organized by NCNW and U.N. HABITAT, as part of the United Nations International Year of the Shelter for the Homeless (IYSH) in 1987. At the end of the Housing section are subject files that include writings by NCNW members and others on women and housing.
  NCNW's comprehensive education and employment training program for public housing tenants provided job orientation, skills training and job placement, leadership training, and adult education. It also offered support and technical assistance to newly formed tenant associations. Once established, the tenant associations joined the Williamsburg/Greenpoint Federation of Public Housing Developments, coordinated by NCNW's local affiliate, Neighborhood Women of Williamsburg/Greenpoint. Records of the public housing tenant program include general administration files of the New York City Housing Authority and the Community Service Society, which provided both funding and administrative assistance to the tenant training program [see also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Development]; and the files of Bertha Gilkey, NCNW National Steering Committee member who helped develop NCNW's tenant program, based on her highly successful work organizing tenants at Cochran Gardens, a public housing development in St. Louis. Also included are the administrative files of the Williamsburg/Greenpoint Federation of Public Housing Developments; and files on various tenant associations the New York City area.
  The International subseries documents NCNW's participation in the international Women and Community Development movement. In 1985, NCNW and other grassroots women leaders formed the international grassroots network, GROOTS (Grassroots Organizations Operating Together in Sisterhood), for which NCNW is the North American representative. The section on GROOTS in this subseries includes correspondence, minutes, conference material and publicity for the the early organizing of GROOTS, as well as their efforts to ensure grassroots women's participation in several international women's conferences, including the U.N.'s Fourth World Conference on Women in Beijing in 1995. In the late 1980s, NCNW achieved consultative status with the United Nations' Economic and Social Council (UNESCO). As an official Non-governmental organization (NGO), NCNW recently opened an office at the United Nations where it works to provide practical assistance and advocates for low-income women around the world who are working to improve their communities. The United Nations files document NCNW's and GROOTS' participation in the international conferences on women sponsored by the U.N. Other organizations and projects represented in this subseries include HABITAT International [see also Housing and tenants], the Overseas Education Fund, which funds economic development projects for poor women (Jan Peterson was elected to serve on Board of O.E.F. in 1985); and the German Marshall Fund, a supporter of research projects on community women's leadership. [See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Development.]
  The Leadership program is another core program of NCNW that aims to develop and support leadership qualities among women active in their communities. IT offers leadership training at national and regional conferences, and in conjunction with its local Employment, Education, and Tenant training programs. Support groups are integral to the Leadership Program and include consciousness-raising sessions to allow neighborhood women to develop an awareness of how oppression based on class, ethnicity, race or gender might impede their sense of empowerment as leaders. This sub-series is divided into five sections: Administration, Local training, Support groups, National training, and Subject files. For related material, see SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Individuals-Lisel Burns (Leadership coordinator).
  NCNW's Resource Center, located at the Brooklyn office, serves as an information and referral center for individuals and grassroots organizations. The Resource Center has provided, at various times, technical assistance, education and training materials, a Speaker's Bureau, and workshops on a variety of topics. [See also Miscellaneous projects, and conferences or events.] In the late 1970's, the Resource Center was part of "Proje-ct Interchange," a program designed to encompass all of NCNW's outreach and networking activities, as well as administering research and documentation projects in the community. Eventually the public relations, networking, and membership activities were allocated to other administrative areas. [See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Membership; and Public relations.] This subseries includes administrative files of the Resource Center, such as project descriptions, proposals, meeting minutes, correspondence, and reports, as well as documentation on the early planning and implementation of Project Interchange. Also included here are files on NCNW's documentation projects, the Cultural Exchange Project, which involved oral histories of poor and working-class women of Williamsburg-Greenpoint in community leadership roles, and the production of the film "Metropolitan Avenue: Community Women in a Changing Urban Neighborhood," which documented NCNW's activities in Brooklyn. Both projects were administered by Christine Noschese. [See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Individuals-Christine Noschese; SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS; and SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL.]
  Finally, the Resource Center library includes directories of local services, bulletin board notices, and subject files. The subject files include unpublished papers, many written by NCNW members, as well as articles, pamphlets, clippings, and other printed material. Topics include class, ethnicity, women's health, local history, grassroots organizing, women's rights, and NCNW itself. Note that the subject files were reconstructed by the archivist and may include files not originally from the Resource Center. There may also by files located in other series that were part of the Resource Center such as papers and articles on specific NCNW programs that can be found under those programs and files on organizations that are under SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS.
  The Women's Public Works (WPW) project was also referred to as the Neighborhood Women's Mother Self-help Program, or the Minority Female Single Parent Program. A five-year program funded by the Rockefeller Foundation, WPW targeted low-income minority women heads of household, many of whom were receiving welfare benefits. Eligible women participated in NCNW's World of Work job orientation program then, depending on their education and job training needs, were referred to the education and/or employment training programs. These records include administrative files for the most part, such as publicity, proposals, reports, funding files, and correspondence. Since the participants took part in various NCNW programs, including Employment, Education, Leadership, and Support services, related material can be found under each of those programs.
  Women's Survival Space (also called the Center for the Elimination of Violence in the Family) was a joint project of NCNW, the Mayor's Task Force on Rape, and the Brooklyn YWCA to provide shelter to abused women and their children, as well as to conduct research and provide community education on the issue of violence in the family. Opened in 1976, it was the first battered women's shelter in New York State and became a national prototype for developing safe space for women. The shelter was soon operating independently of NCNW, although NCNW program participants helped staff the shelter as interns. The records include early planning meetings, correspondence, funding files, project descriptions, reports, and resource files.
  The Youth subseries includes records of NCNW's "You Can Stand on Your Own Two Feet" Community School which opened in 1986. Still in existence, the school offers an education and job-training alternative for high school dropouts, ages 16 to 21. The comprehensive program offers a basic curriculum leading towards a high school equivalency degree (G.E.D.), job preparation (through the "World of Work" course), job skills training, and personal development including leadership training, individual and peer counseling, and theater workshop. The "Four-Step Program" is a component of the school for young women, which includes pregnancy prevention education and childcare training. Other projects represented here include a Summer Youth Program of the mid-1970s that combined recreation and employment opportunities.
  The subseries on Miscellaneous projects, conferences, and events include a few projects unrelated to any of the above programs. There is a small amount of material on the Brooklyn "Legal project" of the 1970s, which proposed a Neighborhood Law Center to fill gaps in existing legal services, including a law library, and workshops for community women on legal issues. It is not clear from the records whether this project was ever funded and implemented. There is material related to local women-run businesses sponsored by NCNW such as "The Corner Store" and the Cooperative for the Production of Hand-Woven Fabrics. Conferences sponsored by NCNW but not directly related to any program are also filed here. [See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-National meetings and conferences; and conferences under specific programs.] Conferences not sponsored by NCNW are in SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS. There is documentation of workshops on topics such as classism, self-improvement, and anti-rape. Some or all of these may have been workshops offered through the Resource Center. The miscellaneous events include fundraisers, film showings, "Neighborhood speak-outs," awards nights, and NCNW's open house and tenth anniversary.
- SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS 1974-1991, 4.5 linear ft.
  The series is arranged alphabetically by name of organization or conference.
  This series consists of records of NCNW affiliates and resource files on many other local and national community and grassroots organizations. Files on conferences sponsored by other organizations are also included. There is a substantial amount of material on organizations with which NCNW worked closely or to which it belonged, such as the Williamsburg-Greenpoint Community Planning Board, the National Association of Neighborhoods, and the St. Nicholas Neighborhood Preservation Project. The material on the Community Planning Board, a branch of the New York City's Area Policy Boards, documents neighborhood development projects such as the Williamsburg Coalition for Quality Housing, an innovative solution to deal the city's lack of affordable housing and severe homeless problem.
  Numerous women's grassroots organizations represented in this series document the women's movement, including the planning committee for International Women's Year, the Summer Institute in Women's History, the Brooklyn College Women's Center, the Women's Action Alliance, the New York Women's Funding Coalition, Women of Many Voices, and Carroll Gardens Neighborhood Women.
  Additional material on affiliated organizations can be found under SERIES II. PROGRAMS, in particular the organizations which participated in Project Open Doors filed under Employment; and tenant associations filed under Housing and tenants. Some international organizations are filed under SERIES II. PROGRAMS-International. For lists of NCNW affiliates, see SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Membership.
  [See also SERIES II. PROGRAMS-International]
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS circa 1970s-1990s, .75 linear ft.
  This series contains photographic prints, color photocopies of images, contact sheets, negatives, and slides documenting local, national and international NCNW events, conferences, and workshops, as well as neighborhood scenes, individuals and groups. Included are many images used in NCNW publications and in publicity for programs.
  [See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Public relations] There are also photographs of the women's march on New York's City Hall to protest cuts in CETA funding in 1980. [See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION - Development.]
- SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS circa 1976-1990s, 1 linear ft.
  Audiotapes include oral history interviews, discussion groups, and meetings of NCNW members. Most are recorded interviews and planning meetings for the Ethnic Heritage Film Project produced by Christine Noschese, circa 1979 [see also SERIES II. PROGRAMS--Resource Center] and are a unique source of raw material, including discussions on topics such as ethnicity, class, women's leadership, Brooklyn history, and early NCNW history.
  Videotapes document NCNW activities and the stories of women in affiliated organizations in East Harlem, New York and in the Northwest, including footage for a documentary on NCNW produced by Christine Noschese, Metropolitan Avenue: Community Women in a Changing Urban Neighborhood.
  Many of the videotapes from this collection have been digitized and are available to view online.
  [For more information on NCNW film projects, see SERIES II. PROGRAMS-Resource Center-Documentation projects. See also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Individuals-Christine Noschese.]
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1974-1996
  - General
    - Documents: By-laws, Certificate of incorporation, 1974-79, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Organization structure and planning
      [See also Local-Planning; and National meetings]
      - Organization charts, 1979-80, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - Structure outlines, 1982-85 (Box 1, Folder 4-6)
      - Goals, "Objectives and principles," undated (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
      - Consultants, 1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
      - Restructuring, 1979-82
        - Membership and Structure Committee: report, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        - Task Force on Structure, 1979-82 (Box 1, Folder 11-13)
        - Staff meeting on structure, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - Restructuring, 1986
        - Board decision and letter of agreement, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        - National meetings, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        - Structure Committee, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 17)
        - Transition Task Force: report, 1986-87 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        - Unit heads: meeting and questionnaire, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - Reports, 1975-84, undated (Box 1, Folder 20-28)
        [See also National Corporate Board; Individuals; and reports under individual PROGRAMS]
  - National Corporate Board of Directors
    - General (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1975-85 (Box 2, Folder 2-5)
    - Meetings, 1975-87, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 6-18)
      [See also National meetings; and SERIES II. PROGRAMS-Leadership development-National]
    - Members: biographical information and lists, 1976, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 1-4)
    - Reports (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
      [See also General; Individuals (Directors); and SERIES II. PROGRAMS-projects]
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
    - "Dialogue on the organization, goals, and needs of the NCNW" (interview of Director, Christine Noschese, by Board members): transcript, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified drafts and notes, 1977-81 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National Advisory Board
    - General: organization and resolutions, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10-11)
    - Correspondence, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Meetings: minutes, agendas, notes, and printed material, 1978-82 (Box 3, Folder 13-14)
    - Members: lists, undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Task forces
      - General: list, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Communication, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Economic development (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - National Steering Committee
    - Correspondence, 1979-87 (Box 3, Folder 19-23)
    - Meetings: minutes, agendas, notes, and printed material, 1974-87, undated (Box 4, Folder 1-10)
    - Subjects
      - Budgets in pending proposals: memorandum, 1980 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - "Monthly check-in" form, undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Personnel and salaries: printed material, 1979, undated (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
        [See also Staff-Personnel]
      - Miscellaneous: notes and printed material, 1980, undated (Box 4, Folder 15)